<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Karan Luthra</title><link href="http://karanluthra.in/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://karanluthra.in/blog/feeds/trojita.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://karanluthra.in/blog/</id><updated>2015-08-17T00:00:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Akademy 2015!</title><link href="http://karanluthra.in/blog/2015/08/akademy-2015/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-08-17T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Karan Luthra</name></author><id>tag:karanluthra.in/blog,2015-08-17:2015/08/akademy-2015/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently got the chance to be an Akademy attendee, and the experience was fantastic. It was the first time I would travel out of India for a FOSS conference, and I was excited as hell for getting a word of support from the Akademy team for helping me by funding the travel and accomodation. Thanks to KDE for making it possible for me to travel from India and meet my GSoC mentor and other hackers from the international KDE Community at large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="I love Akademy" src="/images/akademy/ilove.png" title="I love Akademy" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Akademy is the annual world summit of the KDE community, which includes artists, organizers, evangelists and developers of KDE software. This year it was hosted at the beautiful city of La Coruña in Galicia, Spain. The &lt;a href="https://conf.kde.org/en/akademy2015/public/schedule/2015-07-25"&gt;first day&lt;/a&gt;, 25th July, featured the &lt;a href="https://conf.kde.org/en/akademy2015/public/events/270"&gt;lightening talk by Jan about Trojitá&lt;/a&gt; which demoed the loading of a half-a-million messages large mailbox in about 15 seconds, and spoke about the works in progress and roadmap. Another lightening talk that I liked was the one that taught how to deal with jerks by Jens, &lt;a href="https://conf.kde.org/en/akademy2015/public/events/249"&gt;"your work is bad and you should feel bad"&lt;/a&gt;. The references to Futurama characters made it even more relatable, while Jens is a very engaging speaker already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Trojita fast" src="/images/akademy/trojita-fast.jpg" title="Trojita" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://conf.kde.org/en/akademy2015/public/schedule/2015-07-26"&gt;second day&lt;/a&gt; was as packed with great talks as the previous day, and was flagged off by &lt;a href="https://conf.kde.org/en/akademy2015/public/events/279"&gt;Lydia's keynote&lt;/a&gt; Evolving KDE, also followed by a BoF session later that gave everybody a chance to voice their vision for KDE. Trojitá uses Gerrit for continuous integration/patch reviewing and while there were many sessions around Phabricator as well, Jan spoke about how Gerrit makes life easier for the Trojitá maintainer in his &lt;a href="https://conf.kde.org/en/akademy2015/public/events/269"&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second day also concluded the main conference, so we had the photo session amidst drizzling rain (Galicia has hundreds of names to describe different types of rains) and the annual award ceremony too. 
&lt;img alt="Group Pic" src="/images/akademy/group.jpg" title="Group Pic" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Original picture &lt;a href="http://byte.kde.org/~duffus/akademy/2015/groupphoto/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certificates were open to be signed by community members, which is an excellent way to symbolize how KDE is a community more than any other kind of organization. Congratulations to winners:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Application Award" src="/images/akademy/award-app.jpg" title="Application Award" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best Application: Milian Wolff and the KDevelop team for their work on KDevelop&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Non Application Award" src="/images/akademy/award-non-app.jpg" title="Non Application Award" /&gt;
Best Non-Application: Jens Reuterberg &amp;amp; the Visual Design Group for The Breeze interface design&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Award Kde Connect" src="/images/akademy/award-jury.jpg" title="Award Kde Connect" /&gt;
Jury's Award: Albert Vaca for the KDE Connect application&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Award CI" src="/images/akademy/award-ci.jpg" title="Award CI" /&gt;
Jury's Award: Scarlett Clark for her work advancing the continuous integration infrastructure to more platforms and module&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Award Organizers" src="/images/akademy/award-organizing.jpg" title="Award Organizers" /&gt;
The organizing team at the university were majorly volunteers of the foss club called GPUL and they got an award for organization, for the relentless hard work they put and pulled off such a large scale event out of university. :D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remaining days at Akademy were planned BoFs or mostly time spent in the hacking area, apart from this one day I spent almost two hours and all subsequent nights at the Sliding Block puzzle game (who said GCompris is for kids? Try level 13 ;). I really got excited about projects like KDE Connect, WikiFM and spent time speaking with their developers. It'd be great to spend some free time (I am soon going to get some days off work) on these projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday we had a great terrace party hosted at Terraza which brought the other sides of all us geeks when everybody made use of the unlimited drinks, gorged on finger food and danced together. 
&lt;img alt="Terrace Party at Terraza" src="/images/akademy/terraza.jpg" title="Terrace Party at Terraza" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was really an ice breaking session for most of us, and also when the Indian group started getting comfortable with the rest. Here's a pic of Alex with those of us from Kde India.
&lt;img alt="Alex and friends" src="/images/akademy/terazza-alex.jpg" title="Alex and friends" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day we had the day trip, and we went to the Aquarium Finisterrae and then to the Tower of Hercules. Pictures speak :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="My Escape" src="/images/akademy/myshot.jpg" title="My Escape" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Pictures of the Pacific" src="/images/akademy/scene-pacific.jpg" title="Pictures of the Pacific" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Pictures of the Pacific 2" src="/images/akademy/scene-pacific2.jpg" title="Pictures of the Pacific 2" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Pictures of the Pacific 3" src="/images/akademy/scene-pacific3.jpg" title="Pictures of the Pacific 3" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Me Again" src="/images/akademy/me.jpg" title="Me Again" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Fish Bro" src="/images/akademy/fish-bro.jpg" title="Fish Bro" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Fish bro 2" src="/images/akademy/fish-bro2.jpg" title="Fish bro 2" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="That's a shark!" src="/images/akademy/shark.jpg" title="That's a shark!" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Jigar Swag" src="/images/akademy/jigar-swag.jpg" title="Jigar Swag" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Multilegged" src="/images/akademy/multilegged.jpg" title="Multilegged" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Non Navy Seals" src="/images/akademy/seals-non-navy.jpg" title="Non Navy Seals" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Tower of Hercules" src="/images/akademy/hercules.jpg" title="Tower of Hercules" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We sure made a lot of new friends, apart from putting a face to the names we worked with earlier, via IRC and emails. Here's a pic from the Airport while leaving A Coruña. 
&lt;img alt="New Friends" src="/images/akademy/new-friends.jpg" title="New Friends" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A huge kudos to the team at GPUL for pulling off such a great event and thanks to KDE e.v. and the whole KDE Community for such a great experience. Special mention to GPUL for the stickers to take back home. :)
&lt;img alt="GPUL" src="/images/akademy/gpul.jpg" title="GPUL" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this was the last mediterrainian sunset, before I left Spain for India. :)
&lt;img alt="Farewell Sunset" src="/images/akademy/sunset-farewell.jpg" title="Farewell Sunset" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pictures:
All these pictures are clicked by myself, from my Google Nexus 5. I am waiting for more pictures from Jan and Jigar, who were surely better equipped than me. Pictures aggregated so far can be found at the &lt;a href="https://community.kde.org/Akademy/2015/Photos"&gt;Akademy Photos&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="trojita"></category><category term="kde"></category><category term="foss"></category></entry><entry><title>conf.kde.in 2015</title><link href="http://karanluthra.in/blog/2015/05/conf-kde-amrita-15/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-05-24T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Karan Luthra</name></author><id>tag:karanluthra.in/blog,2015-05-24:2015/05/conf-kde-amrita-15/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I started a new life with working at &lt;a href="http://research.aspiringminds.com"&gt;Aspiring Minds Research&lt;/a&gt; right after Google Summer of Code's coding period got over in late August 2014, and it has since then kept me more involved than I could imagine before. But it was a great feeling when I got an email from &lt;a href="http://blog.shantanu.io"&gt;Shantanu&lt;/a&gt; in early March, reminding me to be a part of conf.kde.in 2015 in Amritapuri, Kerala. Last year I had to cancel all booked travel to DAIICT, Gandhinagar for conf.kde.in 2014 when my university scheduled exams on the conference dates, so Shantanu's mail hinted to me at a dream finally coming true. I sent a &lt;a href="https://conf.kde.org/en/india2015/public/events/216" title="Link to proposal"&gt;talk proposal&lt;/a&gt; as soon as I could, and KDE India was kind enough to accept my proposal and sponsor my travel and accomodation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This news was positively recieved by my employer and team mates, and I couldn't have gone ahead without the kind of support I got from them. A week before the event the CTO invited me to present a mock talk as a Friday session (the whole RnD team gets together every Friday to share ideas), and I got detailed feedback for each part of the talk. I was all geared up to meet KDE India and the excited college kids at Amrita Vishwa Vidyapeetham. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First one to meet was &lt;a href="http://www.somsubhra.com/"&gt;Somsubhra&lt;/a&gt;, who contributes to Krita and was a final year student at DAIICT, last year's hosts. We arrived at Trivandrum airport together, where our very hardworking host Tharun received us. We were lucky to get AC Cab for the ~100 km journey to Amritapuri. We took a detour to pick up &lt;a href="http://nibrahim.net.in/"&gt;Noufal&lt;/a&gt; (who was going to present the keynote the next day) and on our way back I had a lot of questions to ask about the work he did at &lt;a href="https://archive.org/index.php"&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/pyconindia"&gt;PyCon&lt;/a&gt;. The talk only got more interesting when during dinner, Noful started talking about his fondness towards using minimal window managers for a GUI dekstop (he said he used xmonad), the power of the command line (around which he'd give the keynote) and his interest in Calligraphy. Then I met Shantanu, Pradeepto, Harish, Tony, Pinak, Devaja, and Jigar and after quick intros with all of them, we headed to the guest house, for it had been a long day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;DAY 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event was flagged off by a prayer and lamp lighting (reminded me of the cultural richness of my school functions) and a formal inaugration by the senior-most of the college, who welcomed the KDE India community and invited Noful for the keynote. Noful gave the kind of keynote I had never heeard before, and he said he would break as many rules about keynotes as he could that day. He said that he:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Will code live"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Will go into details"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Will go off KDE"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He spoke about the Unix Philosophy of doing only one thing but doing it really well; He advocated writing of programs that could talk over text streams, because that's a universal interface. He emphasized how these well written units can then be used together to solve larger problems. He played Sherlock Holmes and took off to mine a text (Moby Dick) using basic unix commands, out of which wc, unique, awk, paste, and tr were those that I hadn't used (enough) in day-to-day use. The information he extracted using just these basic tools (piped together) gave away most of the book's summary as on Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up were Pradeepto and Shantanu who spoke about the KDE India community and how it has taken form over the years. It was a nice introduction of KDE as a software compilation and not just a Desltop Environment, as the audience (which consisted more of first and second year engineering undergrads) was new to KDE. Shantanu gave a demo of cool KDE applications in action which was followed by Somsubhra's talk on Krita. This one really got the audience excited as watching &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=93lMLEuxSLk" title="Youtube Link"&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt; of professional artwork being made using Krita made everybody believe that this was as much a serious business as it is a fun to use software. The questions being asked had a typical one too, "How is this different from Photoshop", and Somsubhra explained the difference between how an image creation software (Krita) has awesome brush engines vs image manipulation softwares (Photoshop, GIMP) having great filters, etc. People who asked questions got stickers! :D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Post lunch, Pinak spoke about his Season of Kde experience. His talk aimed at making people comfortable with using the tools and processes for contributing to KDE, viz. Internet Relay Chat (IRC), fetching-building-changing-building code, sending patches. This was followed by Shantanu's intro to the Qt framework. By this time, some attendees were curious enough to ask if they would get to learn something hands-on, as these were kids who had contributed before to FOSS projects in some form or the other. There was a hands-on tutorial planned in a huge lab that seated all the attendees and all speakers became mentors to help everyone build a small application using QML. Shantanu took the stage and we had a lot of fun in playing around with QML (the fun part was that I was using QML for the first time myself, and every time Shantanu gave a new task , I'd sit in a corner and try it out myself before I could go and help others). Day 1 was concluded with having made an animated car using QML (which had a box for a chasis but jazzy allow wheels that rotated) :D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A group of students were keen on starting playing with an actual KDE app, and wanted to try out Trojitá. Given that building Trojitá is rather simple, I sat down with this small group aiming to get the source and build the app. There were some glitches with missing packages on their lab's ubuntu systems (cmake, etc), but we were able to build the app, get comfortable with IRC and understand a junior job on the bug list, when we were told that we will miss dinner if we get any more late. :p&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Post dinner, the KDE group went for a walk to the beach (perks of hosting the conference in a coastal location) and had a lot of fun and got to know each other much better. I was happy I could put a face to so many nicks that I saw on the IRC channels since the summer when I started working under GSoC :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Day 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I woke up with the realization that it was the day of my talk and I still hadn't made my slides (I can say I work best under pressure, but actually I procrastinate a little too much :p). So I joined the others by lunch time. By then Rishab had concluded his talk by demoing the game he made using QML (a minimal 2 player ping-pong that only pinged, but never ponged :p) but it was right on point on how easy it is to develop apps using QML. Devaja then gave a tour of KDE Projects (she calls them planets of the Galaxy). It was great to have her as she spoke about the Promo team, writing dot stories and helping in localization of KDE software. She introduced these ways of contributing, which are much different from the experience the rest of us (mostly) carried, i.e. contributing through code. Next was Ashish Madeti, who spoke about MPRIS and demoed controlling music on the KDE Desktop using a mobile phone by volunteers in the audience. The awesome thing about Ashish is that his journey with KDE started exactly an year ago in conf.kde.in, where he was an attendee introduced to KDE. And here he was, sharing his experience as a speaker an year later :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next and the last talk of the conf was mine, and I was going to tell the audience 'Why, What and How to contribute to Trojitá'. The audience had been with us for a long time, so I began with thanking them and telling them they deserved a huge round of applause for patiently absorbing so much of new information given off over the last two days. The thirty or so minutes of my talk really flew by. Looking back, I really enjoyed my talk as there were people asking questions in the middle as well, so I was happy that the ice was broken before I presented my talk. I tried my best to get into details only where needed, but I was pleasantly surprised that many amongst the audience voted to get into details like the application's architecture. I really admire the way Trojitá is written and tried my best to explain the basics of the domain knowledge that would help any one contribute to Trojitá or appreciate it. I was happy right after the talk when while concluding, Shantanu asked the audience which KDE app they'd want to hack on, and there were kids who said Trojitá. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second day ended on a light discussion amongst a smaller group consisting of organizers and speakers in the lab, where everybody pitched in with stories of community building, feedback for this conference, and resolves for future. We were given certificates and some got books too :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The organizers were kind enough to accompany us to a trip to the Ashram to catch the sunset from the 18th floor and for the group pic. It was a lovely time at the Ashram, and Kerala is indeed god's own country. Let the pictures speak their 1k words. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/49657487@N07/sets/72157652087907982/"&gt;Sinny's Set on Flickr&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/anup07/sets/72157651565839337/"&gt;Anup's Set on Flickr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="trojita"></category><category term="kde"></category><category term="foss"></category></entry><entry><title>Half Time: What's up at Trojitá</title><link href="http://karanluthra.in/blog/2014/07/half-time-whats-up-at-trojita/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-07-01T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Karan Luthra</name></author><id>tag:karanluthra.in/blog,2014-07-01:2014/07/half-time-whats-up-at-trojita/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Second half has just begun for the GSoC coding period as well as for the year 2014. We are all more warmed up and pacing up to see another "you will be glued to the second half", but let's take a look at what has kept me involved in Trojitá uptil now. My &lt;a href="http://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/project/details/google/gsoc2014/luthrak/5685265389584384"&gt;project proposal&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href="http://trojita.flaska.net/"&gt;Trojitá&lt;/a&gt; is to:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rewrite Trojitá's SMTP code to enable it to use Trojitá's Sockets, and make it a first class citizen wrt the code quality, robustness, maintainabilty and features.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bring essential features and UI changes that will make Trojitá more usable and ready for a larger user-base.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the second goal consists of small tasks that would also help a newbie (me) get more comfortable with the code, me and my mentors decided to start with these small tasks first. This is what has been done uptil now:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Network Reconnection Attempts&lt;br /&gt;
Trojitá got a feature to automatically start a reconnect attempt cycle whenever there's a network error.&lt;br /&gt;
Previously, whenever the application was hit by a network error, it would switch to offline mode and inform the user by throwing an error message (which would be a modal message box). Now, a message box is still thrown the first time an error is faced and attempts for reconnect begin. To keep in line with Trojitá's prinicples of being less resource hungry and be usable for users with expensive mobile connections, any two reconnect attempts are separated with timeout that doubles every step. So, timeouts go like 5 secs, 10 secs,.. 160 secs, 300 secs (Inspired by the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exponential_backoff"&gt;Exponential Backoff&lt;/a&gt; algorithm I came across in Computer Networks class). And beyond that, attempts are made every 5 mins or manually stopped and restarted by the user. An unattended message box gets closed if network reconnects successfully. &lt;em&gt;Status: Merged in master&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forwarding Support&lt;br /&gt;
Trojitá already had the ability to treat whole messages dragged and dropped into the attachments view in a composer as messages to be forwarded as dot.eml files. In addition to that, trojitá now has a patch (under review atm) that would enable forward as attachment by a single click from the GUI. This includes mangling the subject of the original message and prefixing the "Fwd: " string, as well as marking the original message as $Forwarded. &lt;em&gt;Status: Under &lt;a href="https://git.reviewboard.kde.org/r/118606/"&gt;review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Improvements around Compose Widget  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One improvement is a bug fix that allows any changes to the subject field or the recipients fields to be treated as modifications eligible for storing in a draft. &lt;em&gt;Status: Merged in master&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another improvement is the ability to switch the reply mode { private reply, reply to all, reply to all but me, mailing list reply} from the composer as well (previously, a mode would be picked up at the time of creating the compose reply dialog and switching between modes wasn't possible unless a new dialog be opened). The change of mode triggers the automatic setting up of recipients in the current composer and modifying the recipients puts the reply mode in a fifth state, named "hand picked recipients". This patch is under &lt;a href="https://git.reviewboard.kde.org/r/118802/"&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; and it is yet to be finalised &lt;em&gt;&lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/em&gt; in the compose window should this dropdown menu be placed.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another improvement (that won't be visible to the user) is a change in how a GUI::ComposeWidget is created. A compose widget needs a parent (MainWindow), an MSA(Mail Submissin Agent) object, a settings (QSettings) object and a couple of purpose specific parameters that can pre-fill the fields in the composer (eg: subject, body(quoted), in-reply-to, etc in the case of a "reply"). Due to increasing use-cases for the Compose Widget (Message Forwarding and Message Redirection are two such that are being added in this GSoC project), we felt the need to refactor the ComposeWidget and provide a static API for creating ComposeWidget instances with specific roles. It looks like this:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;script src="https://gist.github.com/karanluthra/37c3f65e229761002958.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/karanluthra/37c3f65e229761002958#file-static-cw"&gt;Gist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second half has started off with shifting the focus onto the bigger task of rewriting the SMTP library. While writing this blog post I realised how it has become a long one to read, and I will try and write about whats up with SMTP more regularly, and hopefully as smaller posts. I find twitter to be a better output stream while in the code-sprint mood and you can follow me on Twitter, I am &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/karanluthra06"&gt;@karanluthra06&lt;/a&gt;. Best wishes to all GSoCers; Let's make this second half the most exciting ever!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers! :)&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="c++"></category><category term="gsoc"></category><category term="trojita"></category><category term="kde"></category><category term="foss"></category></entry><entry><title>This summer I'm flipping bits, not burgers</title><link href="http://karanluthra.in/blog/2014/06/flipping-bits-not-burgers/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Karan Luthra</name></author><id>tag:karanluthra.in/blog,2014-06-10:2014/06/flipping-bits-not-burgers/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wasn't even checking the results that night when I got a congratulatory email from a friend. There was nothing else one could be congratulated for on that night, except for GSoC results. As difficult as it was to believe I found it to be true that my proposal indeed got selected for the 10th &lt;a href="http://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/homepage/google/gsoc2014"&gt;Google Summer of Code&lt;/a&gt;, for the summers of 2014. I will be working under &lt;a href="http://www.kde.org/"&gt;KDE&lt;/a&gt; and my &lt;a href="http://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/project/details/google/gsoc2014/luthrak/5685265389584384"&gt;proposal&lt;/a&gt; aims to improve how &lt;a href="http://trojita.flaska.net"&gt;Trojitá&lt;/a&gt; sends email over SMTP and make it as robust and capable as the IMAP part, the USP of the email client. :D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first contribution to Free and Open Source Software began with a &lt;a href="http://quickgit.kde.org/?p=trojita.git&amp;amp;a=commit&amp;amp;h=6f14132d37666148e2db44be9e051816bb33daca"&gt;patch&lt;/a&gt; for Trojitá in February. It was a feature request that I thought I could work on, and while it took me very long to bring the patch to the quality that could get it merged, it was a different high I experienced when I heard "Ship It!" for the first time in my life, and saw my name in the 'About Trojitá' menu of the email client I had started loving to use. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="About Trojitá - List of Contributors" src="/images/trojita_authors.png" title="About Trojitá - List of Contributors" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the reward of working with open source projects. You can imagine the impact your code can have on thousands (and millions? :D) of users and this motivates you to improve the patch each time it gets returned from a review by mentors. Another encouragement is that open source projects do not care about your exam scores, your university's reputation, or even your majors for that matter! I was thinking hard how to spend the summers after my final semester and before joining the job I have been offered through campus placement, and Google Summer of Code seemed like the dream option to me. However, I was never too sure about getting selected as I am not an experienced developer, so I kept exploring other options while planning to keep contributing to Trojitá at my own, slow pace. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing I did on the morning after the results night, was clear all the bookmarked interships! I have cleared most of the distractions by now, and got another &lt;a href="http://quickgit.kde.org/?p=trojita.git&amp;amp;a=commit&amp;amp;h=7708aaa7fda2877a868a542e9a1335683c9cbdb7"&gt;patch&lt;/a&gt; submitted recently. I am still lagging behind schedule, but it's only going to get better from now :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are even one bit curious about how Open Source projects, GSoC, or Computer Science outside your exam-syllabus works, then keep watching this space. I will try and blog as much as I can about all that I am upto :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers to the Summer of 2014! :D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="GSoC goodies" src="/images/gsoc-diary.jpg" title="GSoC goodies, to begin with :D" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="c++"></category><category term="gsoc"></category><category term="trojita"></category><category term="kde"></category><category term="foss"></category></entry></feed>